<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title type="text">Nelson Reis Blog</title><subtitle type="text">Nelson Reis Blog</subtitle><id>http://www.nelsonreis.net/</id><updated>2015-08-31T22:51:32+01:00</updated><author><name>Nelson Reis</name><uri>http://www.nelsonreis.net</uri><email>nelsonfsr@gmail.com</email></author><generator>Sandra.Snow Atom Generator</generator><link rel="alternate" href="http://www.nelsonreis.net/feed.xml" /><link rel="self" type="text/html" title="Nelson Reis Blog" href="http://www.nelsonreis.net/feed.xml" /><entry><id>http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/09/01/how-to-setup-bower-in-visual-studio-2015/</id><title type="text">How to setup Bower in Visual Studio 2015</title><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href="http://nelsonreis.net/2015/08/31/when-to-use-nuget-and-bower/"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; I've compared &lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/"&gt;NuGet&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://bower.io/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bower&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, explaining where we can use each one in order to make use of their advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Prior notice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio 2015 combined with ASP.NET 5 templates already have Bower integrated by default, but in this example I'm assuming we are developing an ASP.NET 4.6 + MVC 5 web application.&lt;/p&gt;

</summary><published>2015-08-31T23:00:00Z</published><updated>2015-08-31T23:00:00Z</updated><link rel="alternate" href="http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/09/01/how-to-setup-bower-in-visual-studio-2015/" /><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href="http://nelsonreis.net/2015/08/31/when-to-use-nuget-and-bower/"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; I've compared &lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/"&gt;NuGet&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://bower.io/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bower&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, explaining where we can use each one in order to make use of their advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Prior notice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio 2015 combined with ASP.NET 5 templates already have Bower integrated by default, but in this example I'm assuming we are developing an ASP.NET 4.6 + MVC 5 web application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bower depends on &lt;strong&gt;npm&lt;/strong&gt;. What's that? Well, that's &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; package manager, but let's just say that it will help us install Bower and leave it there.
To do that, we'll need to open a &lt;strong&gt;Command Prompt&lt;/strong&gt; on the same folder as our project. If you don't want to leave Visual Studio, you can make use of the &lt;strong&gt;Package Manager Console&lt;/strong&gt; instead.
If you didn't already installed &lt;strong&gt;Git for Windows&lt;/strong&gt;, you'll have to, because Bower let's you install packages directly from a Git endpoint. Go to &lt;a href="http://git-for-windows.github.io/"&gt;Git for Windows&lt;/a&gt; and install.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hands-on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by installing Bower, typing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install -g bower
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will install Bower on a global location so that it will become available at the command line. It still didn't added anything to the project. Before adding packages, let's create a &lt;code&gt;bower.json&lt;/code&gt; file where we'll save all the packages we install in our project (it works just like the &lt;code&gt;packages.config&lt;/code&gt; for NuGet).
If you're using the Package Manager Console, add a new item to the project and select &lt;strong&gt;Bower Configuration File&lt;/strong&gt; (inside Web &gt; General).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're using the Command Prompt, you can add the same file by typing (the command won't work on the Package Manager Console):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bower init
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After typing the command above, Bower will ask for information so it can create a &lt;code&gt;bower.json&lt;/code&gt; file accordingly to the needs of your project. If you don't know what to choose in any of the questions, press &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; and let Bower fill in the default values, which should be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Adding packages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we're ready to add packages to our project. Bower let's you search for packages in the command line, but I rather use Bower's website: http://bower.io/search/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know what to install, you can type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bower install jquery --save
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;--save&lt;/code&gt; argument will add the package to the &lt;code&gt;bower.json&lt;/code&gt;, so later we can update the package or reinstall the missing packages, just like NuGet does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power of Visual Studio shines if you want to avoid the Command Prompt anytime you need to add one more package. Instead, you can install packages by opening the &lt;code&gt;bower.json&lt;/code&gt; file and adding the package to the &lt;code&gt;dependencies&lt;/code&gt; node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as you start typing the name of the package, Visual Studio will search it for you and present the available options &lt;em&gt;intellisense style&lt;/em&gt;. You'll get the same behavior for the version.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/08/31/when-to-use-nuget-and-bower/</id><title type="text">When to use NuGet and Bower</title><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I believe that &lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/"&gt;NuGet&lt;/a&gt; has been one of the most significant tools added to Visual Studio since it was introduced in the 2010 version. It's hard to imagine anyone working on a .NET project over the last few years and still be able to keep NuGet packages out of the solution.
&lt;em&gt;Of course I'm being a bit extreme here, but if that's your case, please make a comment below, I really would like to know more details on that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</summary><published>2015-08-30T23:00:00Z</published><updated>2015-08-30T23:00:00Z</updated><link rel="alternate" href="http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/08/31/when-to-use-nuget-and-bower/" /><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I believe that &lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/"&gt;NuGet&lt;/a&gt; has been one of the most significant tools added to Visual Studio since it was introduced in the 2010 version. It's hard to imagine anyone working on a .NET project over the last few years and still be able to keep NuGet packages out of the solution.
&lt;em&gt;Of course I'm being a bit extreme here, but if that's your case, please make a comment below, I really would like to know more details on that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With NuGet we could easily &lt;em&gt;"add a reference"&lt;/em&gt; to an opensource project, provided it had a NuGet package available, and thus maintain the references updated with a simple action on the UI. That's what helped to drive the .NET development community towards opensource initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;So, is NuGet dead?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from it! But despite all the goodness that NuGet brought to the .NET world (or should I say sweetness), some bitterness arises when working with web frontend NuGet packages (either in plain ASP.NET or ASP.NET MVC projects).
NuGet packages work great for including compiled external libraries into my projects, so I will definitely continue to use NuGet for the backend stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem with the frontend NuGet packages (CSS and JavaScript) is that when you add them, each one seems to have it's own will, getting scattered all over the project folders, forcing me to find its files in whichever folder it choses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem is that there is a lack of NuGet packages for a lot of very used JavaScript libraries, which are available for other web development communities, or at least the available packages take longer to be updated. That makes it seem as if the .NET web development community is lagging behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Introducing Bower&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with Visual Studio 2015, the recommended method for adding frontend web packages to your projects is using &lt;a href="http://bower.io/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bower&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;a package manager for the web&lt;/em&gt;, as they call it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bower packages get installed to a folder with the name of each package inside a &lt;code&gt;bower_components&lt;/code&gt; folder on the root of your project. No more hunting around the installed files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your team or environment uses other tools besides Visual Studio for web development, Bower brings a more clean path to achieve what others are doing, since it's commonly used amongst web developers from other communities (Node.js, for instance). That also brings a bigger number of available packages, as well as faster updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;NuGet or Bower?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I would recommned all server-side packages to be installed with &lt;strong&gt;NuGet&lt;/strong&gt;, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/packages/Ninject/"&gt;Ninject&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/packages/EntityFramework/"&gt;EntityFramework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/packages/NUnit/"&gt;NUnit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/packages/log4net/"&gt;log4net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all the &lt;a href="http://www.nuget.org/packages?q=microsoft.aspnet"&gt;Microsoft.AspNet&lt;/a&gt; packages (the MVC framework, OWIN, Razor, WebApi, and so on)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you've got the picture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;strong&gt;Bower&lt;/strong&gt;, we stick to the web frontend packages, like the ones below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jquery.com/"&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://github.com/jquery/jquery"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://github.com/twbs/bootstrap"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://angularjs.org/"&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://github.com/angular/angular.js"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://select2.github.io/"&gt;Select2&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://github.com/select2/select2"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.datatables.net/"&gt;DataTables&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://github.com/DataTables/DataTables"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://github.com/mbostock/d3"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://momentjs.com/"&gt;Moment.js&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://github.com/moment/moment/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my next blog post, I'll show you how we can add Bower to a Visual Studio project.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/06/01/sqlsaturday-369-lisbon-2015/</id><title type="text">SQLSaturday #369 Lisbon 2015</title><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last May 16 I attended &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369"&gt;SQLSaturday at Lisbon&lt;/a&gt;, Portugal, a free training event mainly targeted at SQL Server and Data professionals. The event featured a total of 6 session slots distributed over the following 7 (!) tracks: Performance, Business Intelligence, Agile &amp;amp; Cloud, Analytics &amp;amp; NonRelational, DBA, Hands-On Lab and SQL Server 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

</summary><published>2015-05-31T23:00:00Z</published><updated>2015-05-31T23:00:00Z</updated><link rel="alternate" href="http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/06/01/sqlsaturday-369-lisbon-2015/" /><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last May 16 I attended &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369"&gt;SQLSaturday at Lisbon&lt;/a&gt;, Portugal, a free training event mainly targeted at SQL Server and Data professionals. The event featured a total of 6 session slots distributed over the following 7 (!) tracks: Performance, Business Intelligence, Agile &amp;amp; Cloud, Analytics &amp;amp; NonRelational, DBA, Hands-On Lab and SQL Server 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What's in it for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I'm not a SQL Server expert by any means, some of the sessions were just beyond my reach, not that I was afraid of getting my head blown by Paul White (&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/SQL_Kiwi"&gt;@SQL_Kiwi&lt;/a&gt;), Dejan Sarka (&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/DejanSarka"&gt;@DejanSarka&lt;/a&gt;), Mark Broadbent (&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/retracement"&gt;@retracement&lt;/a&gt;) or Milos Radivojevic (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MilosSQL"&gt;@MilosSQL&lt;/a&gt;), to name a few SQL &lt;em&gt;superstars&lt;/em&gt; that I skipped this year, but there was so many to choose from and the quality bar was so high that choices had to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the lineup, I've selected the themes with content that I could leverage in the next few months, especially those related to Business Intelligence, one of the current big trends on the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sessions I attended were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agile BI - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/SteffLocke"&gt;Stephanie Locke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Amazing Power BI vNext - All about the new version of Power BI! - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/rquintino"&gt;Rui Quintino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools and Tips: From accidental to efficient Data Warehouse developer - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/cathrinew"&gt;Cathrine Wilhelmsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PowerBI for Developers - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/RuiRomano"&gt;Rui Romano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python and R for SQL Server and Business Intelligence: Be a data analysis Rock Star! - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/jenstirrup"&gt;Jen Stirrup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL vNext Business Intelligence - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/bvbasto"&gt;Bruno Basto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The key takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last year we had the chance to grasp some real use cases of Power BI (first launched in 2013). This year, Microsoft has shown some &lt;a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/powerbi/archive/2015/05/08/a-fresh-new-look-for-the-power-bi-preview.aspx"&gt;major improvements&lt;/a&gt; on this platform and started to reveal a development model on top of it (still in the works) which will allow for a lot more possibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another gap that Microsoft was needing to bridge was a solution for cross-platform dashboards, that could be fed by multiple kinds of data sources. I think that is now solved with the &lt;a href="http://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2015/04/14/microsoft-acquires-mobile-business-intelligence-leader-datazen"&gt;acquisition of DataZen&lt;/a&gt; and the inclusion of the product into the SQL Server Enterprise package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's becoming increasingly more difficult to justify some enterprise policies that want to keep organization data outside cloud services, Microsoft Azure is just not stopping to release new gems every other week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new Microsoft embraces all kind of technology we can imagine. One more proof of that is the integration of R in the upcoming SQL Server 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a lot of opportunities for improvement of my skills on solution development within the Microsoft SQL Server stack. The sessions from &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369/Sessions/Details.aspx?sid=25275"&gt;Stephanie Locke&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369/Sessions/Details.aspx?sid=11235"&gt;Cathrine Wilhelmsen&lt;/a&gt; were just amazing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this one day, a good part of the SQL community throughout the world came together, and if you were around and missed it, to bad for you. But there is hope, because these &lt;a href="http://www.sqlport.com/sql-server/sobre-sqlport"&gt;amazing organizers&lt;/a&gt; are already setting up &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/429"&gt;SQLSaturday Oporto&lt;/a&gt; for October 3. Go ahead and register now!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/05/15/and-so-i-blog/</id><title type="text">And so I blog</title><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to setup a blog for myself for quite some time. Today, finally, I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be asking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"A blog?! That's so outdated, right?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I don't believe so, and if you work on any kind of software development, I'm pretty sure you already found some cool solution to a problem you were having on a random guy's blog, and couldn't find it anywhere else on the &lt;em&gt;interwebs&lt;/em&gt;. Yeah, &lt;em&gt;random guy&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8482; rocks!&lt;/p&gt;

</summary><published>2015-05-14T23:00:00Z</published><updated>2015-05-14T23:00:00Z</updated><link rel="alternate" href="http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/05/15/and-so-i-blog/" /><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to setup a blog for myself for quite some time. Today, finally, I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be asking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"A blog?! That's so outdated, right?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I don't believe so, and if you work on any kind of software development, I'm pretty sure you already found some cool solution to a problem you were having on a random guy's blog, and couldn't find it anywhere else on the &lt;em&gt;interwebs&lt;/em&gt;. Yeah, &lt;em&gt;random guy&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8482; rocks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ok, but aren't there enough blogs, already?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of them, of course, but I believe that the Internet has enough room for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do you believe that someone will actually read it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will write mainly for myself, so that I can later find the solutions I've once found and meanwhile forgot about. Why keep something like that on your head when you can easily look it up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you're writing for yourself, couldn't you keep it private?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years I've learned that if you have a problem or a solution of some sort that you find useful, other people could also relate to that and find usefulness on what you've done. Why keep it all to yourself when you can share it with the community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, those are my viewpoints about blogging, talking to this imaginary and very skeptical person, dear reader and future self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that on future posts you can find something valuable. In the meantime, you can start by following my blog or contact me anytime you want.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>