<rss xmlns:a10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Nelson Reis Blog</title><link>http://www.nelsonreis.net/rss.xml</link><description>Nelson Reis Blog</description><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/06/01/sqlsaturday-369-lisbon-2015/</guid><link>http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/06/01/sqlsaturday-369-lisbon-2015/</link><author>nelsonfsr@gmail.com</author><category>Community</category><category>SQL Server</category><title>SQLSaturday #369 Lisbon 2015</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Last May 16 I attended &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369"&gt;SQLSaturday at Lisbon&lt;/a&gt;, Portugal, a free training event mainly targeted at SQL Server and Data professionals. The event featured a total of 6 session slots distributed over the following 7 (!) tracks: Performance, Business Intelligence, Agile &amp;amp; Cloud, Analytics &amp;amp; NonRelational, DBA, Hands-On Lab and SQL Server 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-05-31T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last May 16 I attended &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369"&gt;SQLSaturday at Lisbon&lt;/a&gt;, Portugal, a free training event mainly targeted at SQL Server and Data professionals. The event featured a total of 6 session slots distributed over the following 7 (!) tracks: Performance, Business Intelligence, Agile &amp;amp; Cloud, Analytics &amp;amp; NonRelational, DBA, Hands-On Lab and SQL Server 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What's in it for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I'm not a SQL Server expert by any means, some of the sessions were just beyond my reach, not that I was afraid of getting my head blown by Paul White (&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/SQL_Kiwi"&gt;@SQL_Kiwi&lt;/a&gt;), Dejan Sarka (&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/DejanSarka"&gt;@DejanSarka&lt;/a&gt;), Mark Broadbent (&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/retracement"&gt;@retracement&lt;/a&gt;) or Milos Radivojevic (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MilosSQL"&gt;@MilosSQL&lt;/a&gt;), to name a few SQL &lt;em&gt;superstars&lt;/em&gt; that I skipped this year, but there was so many to choose from and the quality bar was so high that choices had to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the lineup, I've selected the themes with content that I could leverage in the next few months, especially those related to Business Intelligence, one of the current big trends on the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sessions I attended were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agile BI - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/SteffLocke"&gt;Stephanie Locke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Amazing Power BI vNext - All about the new version of Power BI! - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/rquintino"&gt;Rui Quintino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools and Tips: From accidental to efficient Data Warehouse developer - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/cathrinew"&gt;Cathrine Wilhelmsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PowerBI for Developers - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/RuiRomano"&gt;Rui Romano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python and R for SQL Server and Business Intelligence: Be a data analysis Rock Star! - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/jenstirrup"&gt;Jen Stirrup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL vNext Business Intelligence - &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/bvbasto"&gt;Bruno Basto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The key takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last year we had the chance to grasp some real use cases of Power BI (first launched in 2013). This year, Microsoft has shown some &lt;a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/powerbi/archive/2015/05/08/a-fresh-new-look-for-the-power-bi-preview.aspx"&gt;major improvements&lt;/a&gt; on this platform and started to reveal a development model on top of it (still in the works) which will allow for a lot more possibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another gap that Microsoft was needing to bridge was a solution for cross-platform dashboards, that could be fed by multiple kinds of data sources. I think that is now solved with the &lt;a href="http://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2015/04/14/microsoft-acquires-mobile-business-intelligence-leader-datazen"&gt;acquisition of DataZen&lt;/a&gt; and the inclusion of the product into the SQL Server Enterprise package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's becoming increasingly more difficult to justify some enterprise policies that want to keep organization data outside cloud services, Microsoft Azure is just not stopping to release new gems every other week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new Microsoft embraces all kind of technology we can imagine. One more proof of that is the integration of R in the upcoming SQL Server 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a lot of opportunities for improvement of my skills on solution development within the Microsoft SQL Server stack. The sessions from &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369/Sessions/Details.aspx?sid=25275"&gt;Stephanie Locke&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/369/Sessions/Details.aspx?sid=11235"&gt;Cathrine Wilhelmsen&lt;/a&gt; were just amazing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this one day, a good part of the SQL community throughout the world came together, and if you were around and missed it, to bad for you. But there is hope, because these &lt;a href="http://www.sqlport.com/sql-server/sobre-sqlport"&gt;amazing organizers&lt;/a&gt; are already setting up &lt;a href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/429"&gt;SQLSaturday Oporto&lt;/a&gt; for October 3. Go ahead and register now!&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/05/15/and-so-i-blog/</guid><link>http://www.nelsonreis.net/2015/05/15/and-so-i-blog/</link><author>nelsonfsr@gmail.com</author><category>General</category><title>And so I blog</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to setup a blog for myself for quite some time. Today, finally, I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be asking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"A blog?! That's so outdated, right?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I don't believe so, and if you work on any kind of software development, I'm pretty sure you already found some cool solution to a problem you were having on a random guy's blog, and couldn't find it anywhere else on the &lt;em&gt;interwebs&lt;/em&gt;. Yeah, &lt;em&gt;random guy&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8482; rocks!&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-05-14T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to setup a blog for myself for quite some time. Today, finally, I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be asking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"A blog?! That's so outdated, right?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I don't believe so, and if you work on any kind of software development, I'm pretty sure you already found some cool solution to a problem you were having on a random guy's blog, and couldn't find it anywhere else on the &lt;em&gt;interwebs&lt;/em&gt;. Yeah, &lt;em&gt;random guy&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8482; rocks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ok, but aren't there enough blogs, already?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of them, of course, but I believe that the Internet has enough room for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do you believe that someone will actually read it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will write mainly for myself, so that I can later find the solutions I've once found and meanwhile forgot about. Why keep something like that on your head when you can easily look it up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you're writing for yourself, couldn't you keep it private?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years I've learned that if you have a problem or a solution of some sort that you find useful, other people could also relate to that and find usefulness on what you've done. Why keep it all to yourself when you can share it with the community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, those are my viewpoints about blogging, talking to this imaginary and very skeptical person, dear reader and future self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that on future posts you can find something valuable. In the meantime, you can start by following my blog or contact me anytime you want.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item></channel></rss>